Guide to the Martin Gardner Papers SC0647
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Subject files, Series 2
  - Types of Numbers (Alphabetized), 32 folder(s)
    - S-P Numbers (Sum & Product), undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
      Article, by A.F. Beardon (no date)
    - Square Numbers & Sq. Roots, 1963-2001 (Box 8, Folder 2)
      Trigg on his "Mathematical Quickies"
      Aehle, Truman
      Metzger, James
      Brackney, r.L.
    - Cubes & Highter Powers, 1958-1997 (Box 8, Folder 3)
      Allen, Kenneth
      Pugh, Henry
    - Powers (Mod M), 1994-1999 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Figurates, 1989-1998 (Box 8, Folder 5)
      "On Figurate Numbers", by Istvan Gaal & Akos Pinter, Tech Report No. 93/78, 1993
    - Tetrahedral Numbers, 1958-1991 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Triangular No's, 1980-2000 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Polyhedral No's, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Vampire No's, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Word Play, 51 folder(s)
    - Chess Spells, ONE->NINE, 1995 (Box 63, Folder 15)
      About arranging letters in a grid, so you can spell out numbers
    - Alphabet (Letter Fun), 1996 (Box 63, Folder 16)
    - ABC Lists & Books, 1993 (Box 63, Folder 17)
      Alphabet books (& lists)
    - Ashleigh Brilliant, 1987-1992 (Box 63, Folder 18)
      Pot-Shots
    - Borgmann, Dmitri, 1965-1998 (Box 63, Folder 19)
    - J. A. Lindon [1 of 2], 1966-1987 (Box 63, Folder 20)
      Much humorous poetry (mostly undated)
      Articles from Worm Runners Digest
      "Behind the Surface", by J.A. Lindon, a fancasy (10pp) (typescript)
    - J. A. Lindon [2 of 2], 1965-1995 (Box 63, Folder 21)
      Star numbers
      More poetry, mostly humorous, some math-related
    - Palindromes [1 of 2], 1961-1978 (Box 63, Folder 22)
      Many palindromes, articles on palindromes, articles about people who specialize in palindromes, etc.
      Some J.A. Lindon poetry & palindromes
      "The Poetics of the Palindrome", by Gary Coen, 1977, 44p (typescript)
    - Palindromes [2 of 2], 1967-1999 (Box 63, Folder 23)
      "Llet's PLLay LLama", by Howard Nottage, 1968 (booklet)
      Hunt, Patrick
      Morice, Dave
    - Palindrome Poetry, 1963-1999 (Box 64, Folder 1)
      "Party Trap", by Jennifer Curtis, 1984, 6pp (booklet)
    - S & S Crossword Book - Introduction, 1925-1973 (Box 64, Folder 2)
      Introduction to Simon & Schusters "Crosswords Sereies 107"
      Some references
      Lots of newspaper articles, most on history and popularity of crossword puzzles
      First draft of intorduction
      Barrow, Helen
      Farrar, Margaret
    - "Double Crostic", 1966-1979 (Box 64, Folder 3)
      Articles, obituaries
    - Anagrams [1 of 2], 1960-1999 (Box 64, Folder 4)
      Many anagrams, various types
      "Bibliography of Studies Employing Anagrams", by Charles Haertzen, 1965 (typescript)
      Translation of "Memory, Dreams, Reflections", by C.G. Jung, Appendix V (anagrams at end) (photocoy)
      "On Computing Anagrams", by James A. Wood, 1984 (typescript)
      Golomb, Solomon\
      Woods, James
    - Anagrams [2 of 2], 1999-2000 (Box 64, Folder 5)
      Computer listing of single word anagrams, from Guy Steele, 1999
    - Word Shifts, 1961-1993 (Box 64, Folder 6)
    - Qwerty, 1998 (Box 64, Folder 7)
      1 article (photocopy)
    - Person Names, 1964-1993 (Box 64, Folder 8)
      Regular people
      Promenent people
      Non-existant people, and books, etc.
      McGovern, Eugene
    - Place Names, 1966-1993 (Box 64, Folder 9)
    - Acrostics, 1961-1969 (Box 64, Folder 10)
    - King's Tour Spelling Matrices, 1968-1969 (Box 64, Folder 11)
      Methods of making these
      Munson, John
    - Acronyms, 1961-1988 (Box 64, Folder 12)
    - Bombaugh Project, 1959-1979 (Box 64, Folder 13)
      For annotated edition of "Gleanings for the Curious", by C.C. Bombough (published as "Oddities and Curiosities")
      Notes from National Puzzlers' League
      Hooke, robert
    - Bombaugh - Revisions, 1969-1970 (Box 64, Folder 14)
      Coulthard, John
      Petroski, Henry
    - Long Words, 1959-1965 (Box 64, Folder 15)
    - Spoonerisms, 1957-1994 (Box 64, Folder 16)
    - Unusual Words, 1960-1995 (Box 64, Folder 17)
      Mostly, havning unusual properties
      Newby, Peter
    - Tom Swifties & Elephant Jokes, 1963-1983 (Box 64, Folder 18)
    - Punw, 1961-1999 (Box 65, Folder 1)
      Lindon, John
    - CDB Language, 1981 (Box 65, Folder 2)
    - Knock, Knock, 1936-1981 (Box 65, Folder 3)
      "Knock Knock Featuring Enoch Knox", by Bob Dunn, 1936, Whitman Publishing
      "Knock, Knock - Who's There?", words by Jimmy Tyson & Bill Davies, Misic by Vincent Lopez & Johnny Morris, 1936 (sheet music)
    - Eodermdromes, 1991 (Box 65, Folder 4)
      Non-planar spelling nets
      Bloom, Gary
    - Unusual Poems, 1960-2000 (Box 65, Folder 5)
      Many kinds of poems, including:
      Short Verse (2 or 3 words)
      Clerihew's
      Flexigon Poems
    - Pangrams, 1960-1992 (Box 65, Folder 6)
    - Lee Sallows Pangrams, 1983-1994 (Box 65, Folder 7)
      Sallows pangram machine - checks pangrams (Autograms) of the form "This pangram contains five a's, ..., and six z's".
      "In quest of a Pangram", by Lee Sallows, 1984, 33pp (pamphlet)
    - Skellings' Color Poems, 1979 (Box 65, Folder 8)
      Skellings, Edmund
    - Lipograms, 1952-1995 (Box 65, Folder 9)
      An "E"-less technical article
      An "it"-less technical article, by Norman Gridgeman
    - Shaped Verse, 1961-1983 (Box 65, Folder 10)
    - Garbled Verse Project, 1972-1983 (Box 65, Folder 11)
      Cousins, Norman
    - Word Squares - Palindormic & Latin, 1963-1964 (Box 65, Folder 12)
    - Sator, Arepo, 1957-1982 (Box 65, Folder 13)
      "The Cirencester Word-Square", by Donald Atkinson, 1964, 34pp (booklet)
    - Cryptography, codes, 1973-1999 (Box 65, Folder 14)
    - Beale Cipher, 1972-1981 (Box 65, Folder 15)
      "The Beale Ciphers", The Beale Cypher Association, 1978, 50pp (pamphlet)
    - Voynich MSS., 1988-2000 (Box 66, Folder 1)
      Some articles about MSS itself and about books concerning it
      "The Voynich Manuscript: An Elegant Enigma", by M.E. D'Imperio, 1978, 140pp (photocopy)
    - Raymond Rooussel, 1974-1995 (Box 66, Folder 2)
      Photocopies of articles on and by him
    - California Zodiac Murders, 1981-1990 (Box 66, Folder 3)
      Articles (by Gareth Penn) on Zodiac killers' cyphers
      Penn, Gareth
    - N.Y. Zodiac Copycat, 1996 (Box 66, Folder 4)
      Some web pages on New York Zodiac Killer
    - Mrs. Herndon's Decoding, 1996 (Box 66, Folder 5)
      Of Zodiac cryptograms
    - Misc. Word Play [ 1of 4], 1963-1985 (Box 66, Folder 6)
    - Misc. Word Play [2 of 4], 1959-1993 (Box 66, Folder 7)
      "Speechstuff and Thoughtstuff", by Douglas Hofstadter, 36pp (typescript)
      Jack Green periodical, preliminary edition
    - Misc. Word Play [3 of 4], 1959-1982 (Box 66, Folder 8)
      Gilmer, robert
    - Misc. Word Play [4 of 4], 1956-1983 (Box 66, Folder 9)
      Section with much early (50's) wordplay from Dmitri Borgmann
      Tompkins, Pendleton
- Additional material, Series 3
  - Puzzles
    - Jerry Slocum, Directory of Puzzle Collectors Puzzle Sellers, 35431 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Jerry Slocum, Directory of Puzzle Collectors and Puzzle Sellers, 34425 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Jerry Slocum, Compendium of Checkerboard Puzzles, 30407 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Jerry Slocum and Jacques Haubrich, Compendium of Checkerboard Puzzles, 34182 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Jerry Slocum and Dieter Gebhardt, Puzzles from Catel's Caibnet and BEstelmeier's Magazine 1785 to 1823, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Jerry Slocum, Wire Puzzles Ch'ung-en Yu (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Ruan Liuqi, the Ingenious Puzzle Craftsman of Suzhou; edited by Wei Zhang and Peter Rasmussen, circa 1998 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Die 12 Verhext - Steine Zimpfer Puzzles (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Stewart T. Coffin, Puzzle Craft, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Stewart T. Coffin, Wooden Puzzles, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - William A. Miller, The Official Handbook for Peg Solitaire, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Sivy Farhi, projected book on the soma cube, with letter and c.v., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - James Dalgety, R. Journet and Company; a Brief History of the Company and Its Puzzles, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Norman L. Sandfield, Chinese Ceramic Puzzle Vessels, Feb. 2000 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - gamepuzzles for the joy of thinking - cataloags, 1993-1999 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Multimatch I, II, III, IV Game rules / puzzle designs (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Miscellaneous items (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Mind-bending puzzles by Terry Stickels, a 365-day calendar [4 items], 1997, 1999-2001 (Box 2)
    - Visual Brain Storms, the Smart Thinking Game (Box 2)
    - Tangoes, the Ancient Chinese Puzzle Game with training guide (Box 2)
    - Word Trek, An Adventure from Start to Finish (Box 2)
    - Puzzle pieces for TANGRAM [2 unopened items] (Box 2)
    - Karl Fulves, Punch-Out Puzzle Kit (Box 2)
    - Mathematical curiosities 1, a collection of interesting and curious models...ready to cut out and glue together (Box 2)
    - Magnificent Mazes 1980 Appointment Calendar (Box 2)
    - Two games using Escher images (Box 2)
  - Notebook on Calculus - Probability - Infinite numbers (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - M. C. Escher address book with letter from Garnder to Frank Harary relating his own Escher artworks, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Additional material, Accession ARCH-2003-016
  - Books and articles by or about Martin Gardner, Lewis Carroll; annotated editions of Alice in Wonderland, The Hunting of the Snark, etc. (Box 1)
  - Gardner, Martin, The Flight of Peter Fromm (Box 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Original manuscript (edited), galley proofs, etc.
  - Materials re: The Hunting of the Snark (Box 3)
  - Materials re: The Flight of Peter Fromm, the annotated centennial edition of Lewis Carroll's The Hunting of the Snark (Box 4)
  - Books re: Lewis Carroll (Box 5)
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH-2018-018
  - Pentominoes 6 x 10 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cutler, Bill, "A computer analysis of all 6-piece burrs", 1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Pentominoes 4 x 15 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Pentominoes 5 x 12 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Pentominoes 6 x 10 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bouwkamp, C. J., "Catalog of solutions of the rectangular 3x4x5 solid pentomino problem", 1967 Jul (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bouwkamp, C. J. and A. J. W. Duijvestijn, "Catalogue of simple perfect squared squares of orders 21, through 25", 1992 Nov (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - HEXED, circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Pentomino workshop, Batavia, IL, 1986 Dec 2 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Tribute to Piet Hein; Rube Goldberg Inventions, circa 1997 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Design Science Toys, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Pentominoes Workshop correspondence (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - AGATE "Mathematics for gifted students" v.3, no.1, 1989 Spring (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Wilson, Marguerite, "SOMA puzzle solutions", 1973 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Computer printouts (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - EWS Collectors Evening, 1992 May 14 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Pentomino solutions, 1963 Jun-Jul (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Fontaine, Anne, "An infinite number of plane figures with Heesch Number Two" (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Golomb, Solomon, "Max Delbruck: an appreciation", 1982 Summer (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - World Game Review - Special issue on polyforms, 1989 Dec (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Articles in tribute to Martin Gardner, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Gardner Atlanta gathering, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Dedicated to M.G. by NOB, 1993 Jan (Box 1, Folder 23)